Guide to the Donald H. Balleisen Papers, 1955-1991 RL.11512
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Donald H. Balleisen papers
1955-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Balleisen, Donald H., 1925-1993
RL.11512
2.0 Linear Feet
Attorney for R.J. Reynolds and other corporations. Collection includes assorted files and opinions from legal cases involving R.J. Reynolds, Kentucky Fried Chicken, and other large companies.
Biographical / Historical
Donald H. Balleisen (1925-1993), originally from Brooklyn, served in the U.S. Navy during World War II and graduated from Princeton University (class of 1946). He attended Harvard Law School and subsequently joined a New York law firm. He was secretary and general counsel of Penick and Ford, N.Y., until 1969, when he relocated to Louisville, Kentucky. Balleisen represented R. J. Reynolds and a number of other large corporations as a partner in Greenebaum, Doll, Matthews, and Boone. Balleisen was also an active board member of Louisville's Lincoln Foundation and helped develop the organization's Whitney M. Young Scholars Program, aimed at helping disadvantaged youth reach and pay for college.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Donald H. Balleisen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Edward J. Balleisen in 2017.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of legal materials related to Balleisen's work on R. J. Reynolds acquisitions of Penick and Ford, College Inn Foods, and Patio Foods. Also includes Balleisen's draft of his investigation into R. J. Reynolds' liability for damages following tobacco users' lawsuits beginning in the 1950s; some miscellaneous legal cases from throughout Balleisen's career; and materials from the Lincoln Foundation in Louisville, Kentucky.
Louisville (Ky.) -- History; Legal documents; Business records; Consolidation and merger of corporations; R.J. Reynolds Industries; Kentucky Fried Chicken (Firm)
- R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Company, 1955-1968
  - The Law and Warranty in the Sale of Goods and its Relation to Actions Against Tobacco Companies, by D. Balleisen, 1955 May (Box 1)
  - Penick and Ford, Ltd., Inc.: Acquisition of College Inn Food Products Corporation, 1964 (Volume 3, Volume 4)
  - Acquisition of Assets and Business of Penick and Ford, Ltd., Inc., 1965 (Volume 1)
  - Acquisition by R. J. Reynolds Foods, Inc. of the stock of the Chun King Corporation, 1966 (Volume 5)
  - U.S. vs. R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Co.: Statement of Facts relating to the corn wet milling industry and Penick and Ford, 1966 Apr. 13 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Counsel workpapers: master
  - Acquisition by R. J. Reynolds Foods, Inc. of the Assets and Business of Patio Foods, Inc., 1967 (Volume 2)
  - U.S. vs. R. J. Reynolds Tobacco Co.: Defendant's Interrogatories set no. 2, 1968 (Box 1)
- Other legal cases, 1970-1984
  - Herm, Jutt, Williams, etc. vs Daniel Boone Fried Chicken: Complaints, 1970, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Lester E. Davis vs. Nite Owl Food Mart: Memorandum on behalf of defendents, 1972 (Box 1)
  - UNIT, INC vs. Kentucky Fried Chicken and John Brown, civil suit in New Castle, Del.: Opinion, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Frisch's Restaurants vs. R. R. Preston: Partial Summary Judgment, 1974 (Box 1)
    From Balleisen's work at Greenebaum, Doll, Matthews, and Boone
  - Five Star Gasoline vs. CSC Oil Corp.: Post-Trial Memorandum on behalf of defendant CSC Oil Corp., by D. Balleisen, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Shelby Riggs et al vs. Kentucky: Brief in opposition, by D. Balleisen, P. Nepute, and D. Pitt, 1984 (Box 1)
- Other materials, 1959-1991
  - Job rejection letters for Balleisen from various life insurance companies, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Articles of partnership (draft) for Greenebaum, Doll, Matthews, and Boone, 1977 May 27 (Box 1)
  - Terms of departure for Kaye, Scholer, Fierman, Hays, and Handler, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1986 Jan.-June (Box 1)
  - Greenebaum, Doll, and McDonald: Timesheets for Balleisen's clients, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Lincoln Foundation: Whitney Young Job Corps Center, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Lincoln Foundation: Election, membership, 1990-1991 (Box 1)